Welcome back, everybody.
This is going to be the last
of the more technical talks.
We've done introduction
to Julia, introduction
to differential
equations and plotting.
And this is essentially
introduction to Neuroblox
from a technical point of view.
So you will get familiar
with the structure
of the code in Neuroblox and how
you can contribute your own code
to Neuroblox, writing your own
blox and your own connection
rules.
And from the next
session, so tomorrow
morning, we will get more
into the neuroscience.
I'm going to use all these tools
from the technical sessions
to do computational
neuroscience in Neuroblox.
So what we will go
through is essentially
the structure of Neuroblox
and of its design concepts,
which the main
ones are the blox.
You know blox are
the components.
And you've seen them
as icons in the GUI.
And now, you will see
how they look in code.
And also the connection rules.
The connections are essentially
the edges of the graph
if the blox are the nodes.
And these two things
together essentially
are the core linear blox.
Exactly how I said before, the
types and multiple dispatch
are the core in Julia.
There's not one-to-one mapping
because we will see custom types
in both blox and connections.
But multiple dispatch is mainly
exploited by connection rules.
So yeah, as I said, we have the
types and multiple dispatch.
And when I talk about types, I
mean in particular type trees.
Much like yesterday
or on the exercises
and on the
presentation, where we
show how number,
as a type in Julia,
is a super type above integers
and above floating point--
numbers of any precision.
So that is a small type tree.
Exactly like that in Julia,
we have-- sorry, in Neuroblox,
we have type trees
of all of our blox.
And every node in
that tree could
be either a primitive block
that is neurons or neuron
masses, blox that contain
dynamics in them immediately.
They could be composite
types, so composite blox
that are blox that
contain neurons or neuron
masses in them.
So they could represent
different circuits.
And we also have some
abstract types where,
as you saw in the
exercises yesterday,
you cannot instantiate an
object that is an abstract type.
But abstract types
help us [? as ?] some
hubs in the type tree that
branch out to multiple nodes
and helps us to organize
the type tree better,
and they help with
multiple dispatch.
You will see how.
So this is a partial
view of the type tree
that we have in Neuroblox.
Above all, the most general
type that we have is this type
called abstract blox.
And everything else, every
other blox is a subtype of this.
And here, I'm showing you
four main categories that
are subtypes of abstract blox.
We have neurons, neural masses,
stimuli, and observer blox.
And then if we follow the
tree down towards the leaves,
neuron can be split into--
and again, this is
only a partial view.
But we have, for instance,
abstract [INAUDIBLE] neuroblox,
where we put all of our
bloxes that are explicitly
excitatory in their dynamics.
And likewise,
abstract inhibitory
are innate neuroblox for
inhibitory neuron types.
But we also have neurons that
are just subtypes of neuron.
There's no other
node underneath.
So like a LIF neuron, that's a
leaky integrate and fire neuron,
similar to the generalized
integrate and fire that you saw
in the exercise in the morning.
That just falls under neuron.
There's no other category here.
And because the
neuron can be used
for both excitatory and
inhibitory dynamics,
it doesn't fall in any
other of the two categories.
But if we keep following
the abstract categories,
because in theory, every
abstract category is not
a leaf in the type
tree, it has to be
followed by something else.
Otherwise, there's
no function for it.
We have Hodgkin-Huxley neurons.
That's the H-H
always in your blox.
So have a Hodgkin-Huxley
neuron that is explicitly
designed to be excitatory
and, likewise, one
that is inhibitory.
And for neural masses, these
are also split into multiple.
If I recall correctly,
there is no abstract type
beneath neural mass.
So we only have
different blox that
are neural mass blox
from the literature,
like Wilson-Cowan or
Lauter-Breakspear.
And in the stimulus
category, we have
anything that is an
external stimulus into blox.
That can be
[INAUDIBLE] stimulus.
As you saw in the
category learning task,
we can provide images
that are pixel by pixel
matched to blox as an input.
Or we have blox like
the Poisson spike train
that does exactly what it says.
It just generates spikes
with a Poisson process
that go into your neuron.
And observer blox,
we'll see some of them
on Friday when we
talk about DCM.
So these are like
measurement blox.
These are blox that represent
some experimental measure.
So if you attach that on top
of a block with dynamics,
you can transform some variables
in that blox-- for instance,
its voltage--
into something that is actually
measurable in an experiment--
for instance, [? volt ?] signal.
So here, I just want to show
you a couple of examples
of blox definitions so
you can see how they
look like in the source code.
And you will design some
of these yourselves.
So this is a
Wilson-Cowan, which is
a subtype of neural
mass block using
the syntax for subtyping here.
And as you will see
shortly in the exercises,
the necessary
fields for any blox
are two-- essentially, the
system and the namespace.
The params here is optional.
We have it for some convenience
internally in the code,
but you don't really
need this params.
And the system field is going to
hold the system of differential
equations.
We'll talk more about
namespace tomorrow
when we talk about
circuits, but this
is essentially to designate
where exactly in the hierarchy
of blox is we are right now.
Because if, for
instance, these blox
is a final blox in our
graph, then the namespace
is only the name
of the final model.
But if these blox is
hidden inside another blox
and another blox,
then this namespace
carries that information,
so we know exactly where
we are with each object.
And when you define a
function, which is essentially
a constructor for our blox,
so we need to tell Julia,
essentially, how to construct
an object called Wilson-Cowan.
So this is what this
function is doing.
And this is an
internal constructor.
And it's called internal
because the function
definition, as you can see, is
inside the structure definition.
And we do it like
this for convenience.
And also if you define
an internal constructor,
then that's the
default one, and that's
the only internal constructor
that will be used.
So for instance, you cannot
now define a Wilson-Cowan block
by providing params, and system,
and namespace because we're not
expecting everybody to provide
these three fields as inputs
to a constructor.
We expect somebody to
provide in all the parameters
that the Wilson-Cowan block has.
And you can see these are
all keyword arguments.
And we always stick to keyword
arguments for convenience.
You have to explicitly type the
parameter name and the value
so you know exactly which
parameter you're setting,
what value.
So you supply all
these parameters
that are relevant to your blox.
And then you would
define a set of variables
exactly as you did in the
morning session and also
a set of parameters if needed.
This is done through
parameter scoping here.
Parameter scoping is some
blox function internally
to figure out if your parameters
are shared with other blox.
So you can do that as well.
Say that you have 500 of
these Wilson-Cowan blox,
but you want all of them to
have one common tau v parameter.
This is handled internally by
this parameter scoping function.
The equations--
exactly as before,
you type them out symbolically
using modeling toolkit syntax.
And finally, you just
define your system.
And you supply that
system the namespace
and, optionally, the
parameters in your call
to this new function.
And this new function
is a special function
for any internal constructor
that basically outputs
an object of type Wilson-Cowan.
Because this function is a
constructor, so at the end,
it's going to construct an
object of this type for us.
And likewise, this is the
definition of an alive neuron--
a leaky integrate
and fire neuron.
As you can see, this time,
it's a subtype of neuron.
It's important to
designate this.
And again, as an
input, it takes in all
of the relevant
parameters for the model.
It passes those values to
symbolic parameters here.
And it defines its variables
with some default values,
equations.
And the extra thing
here, of course,
is the spiking, because this
is an integrate and fire
neuron, so we need to
do the spiking manually
exactly how you did with
the [INAUDIBLE] neuron
in the morning.
So in our system
definition here,
we just pass a discrete
event, the spiking event.
And yeah, again, the
same call to new.
This is basically all you need
to write a new [? blox. ?]
Now, because neuron
already comes
with a lot of blox
already implemented--
of course, one way
of looking at them
would be looking directly
at the source code.
If you want to do
that, that's fine.
But I would say an easier way
and a more user-friendly way
is to go through help.
And this is a general
Julia feature.
If you are in a Julia session,
and you type in the question
mark, then it jumps
from the normal Julia
session to this help.
If you type in any
Julia type here,
it's going to give you
essentially the docstring
of that type, which
is essentially
a short documentation
for that type.
And we have written
documentation
like this for our blox.
So if you type, for instance,
help, question mark,
[? alive ?] neuron,
then the output
is this docstring,
essentially, which
describes what this block is,
what these parameters are,
and how you can construct it.
So then there's also a
reference because these blox
comes from the literature.
It's implemented
based on a paper.
So you can know more about this.
So you can know more about
how to use it in your code.
Now, moving on to
connections, as I said,
both blox and connections
have custom types.
And the custom type
for connections
is this connector object.
Essentially, every
connection-- every edge
in our graph, every
connection between two blox
will generate a
connector object.
And that object will
hold all information
about how these two blox
should talk to one another.
And in order to create
these connectors,
we also have
constructor functions.
And these constructors rely on
multiple dispatch, essentially,
to do so.
And the multiple dispatch
relies on the type
of the source blox, the type
of the destination blox.
So we can have
different rules that
are different combinations of a
source block and a destination
blox.
And of course, some
rules are reasonable,
like connecting two
neurons together.
There is a rule for that.
But some rules are
not implementing
[? Neuroblox ?] because we
never expect them to be used.
For instance, if you want to
connect a neuron to a stimulus,
that connection
doesn't apply, and it
doesn't exist in your rules.
But of course, a connection
from a stimulus to a neuron
exists, whether that's a
stimulus, or a Poisson spike
train, or any other.
And now, when you define
a new blox, sometimes--
most of the time, in
fact, it's enough.
If you subtype it as
something-- for instance,
you define a neuron model,
and you subtype that as neuron
or a neural mass subtype
as neural mass block--
that is enough for it to fall
under some connection rule.
So even if you don't
define your own connection
rule, and you only define a--
sorry, a custom blox--
then you should be able to
interface with other blox
because we have some
generic connection rules.
So if Julia doesn't find a
connection rule specifically
for your blox, it's going to
fall back to the generic one.
But of course, if you want to--
if your case is more exotic,
or you want some
specific connection rule,
it's easy to define your own.
So then the generic one will
be replaced by your own.
And what you need to
define a connection rule
is basically essentially
summarized here.
Here, I'm showing you
again a screenshot
from the neural
block source code.
And this is the most
general definition
of a connector object that
takes in-- as you can see,
both of the source block
is just an abstract block.
It could be any type of block.
And the destination blox can
be, again, abstract blox--
anything.
But we don't expect the user
to write connector constructors
like this.
We expect the user to
add their own [INAUDIBLE]
[? pods ?] to these
functions highlighted here.
So we have four
functions that you
can extend with your own rules.
So maybe the most important
one is connection rule.
So if you want to write--
sorry, connection
equations-- if you
want to write your own
connection equations,
you can import this function.
You will see how to do
that in the exercises.
And just write your own
function definition.
And that adds another
dispatch for this function.
So when actually Neuroblox
tries to connect your blox
with another blox, and you have
connection equations defined
for your blox, comma,
and another type of blox,
then it's going to
call your function.
Likewise, you can add the
connection learning rule.
So this applies to
reinforcement learning.
And we will talk about
reinforcement learning
on plasticity on Thursday.
So if you want those
symbolic weights that get
generated every time you add
a connection-- if you want
those weights to update based
on some plasticity rule,
you can write that in a function
called connection learning rule
and extend the sense
with this definition.
Connection callbacks
can be any callbacks
that you would like
to add to connection.
We left this blank for
anything that you want to add.
There are connection
spike effects where,
essentially, specific callbacks
that apply to spiking.
And we have this
separated for convenience
because you will see that
connection spike effects are
easier to write.
And you can write them as,
when this source neuron spikes,
apply these equations.
So again, all you need to do to
write your own custom connection
rule is define all or maybe
some of these four functions.
Sometimes all you want is
some continuous equation
between two blox.
So it's enough to define
connection equations.
But maybe you have neurons, like
the [INAUDIBLE] neuron, which
has this event type spiking.
So you want, at every event, to
affect the destination neuron.
And so in that case, you would
extend the connection spike
effect.
So finally, as I said, because
we have many neurons implemented
in [? Neuroblox, ?]
and actually,
the library is growing, there
can be a combinatorial explosion
of connection rules, because
many of the viable pairs of blox
is together can have
specialized rules.
But you, as a user, if you
want to see what rule applies
to a couple of blox,
you can actually
call this function, what's
called connection rule.
Here, I just defined two bloxes.
You will see how to do this.
And then I call my
connection rule function
with the source neutron first
and the destination neuron,
or blox in general, second,
and then any keyword arguments
because wait here is a keyword
argument that I've just
given it a value of 1.
And then I get a
nice printout that
tells me what
connection am I looking
at, what's the equation that
applies to this connection,
and any other additional things.
For instance, it
tells me the weights
that have been
generated specifically
for this connection.
So when this connection
happens in the model,
I'm going to get a symbolic
parameter generated that is
called weight_w_, the name of
the source neuron, underscore,
the name of the
destination neuron.
And we made it so that these
weights are easy to find.
So maybe you want to print
your weights at the end,
especially if you're
doing learning.
So they're easy
to find like this.
But also this
specific connection,
because it's a layer of neurons
and they have this event type
spiking, also includes
some spike effects.
And you also get a
nice print of this.
So the print tells you that
each time LIF1 spikes, then
it affects the
specific state on LIF2.
So it affects the
[INAUDIBLE] of LIF2
by incrementing it by the
symbolic weight, basically.
But this function applies
to any combination of blox.
So if you're
uncertain about what's
the rule connecting these
two objects together,
you can call this.
And if you're unsatisfied
by the answer,
maybe you can write
your own rule.
And this was the
end, essentially.
So yeah, exactly like
the morning session.
But from now on,
it's going to be
a single notebook per session.
You can just navigate to blox
and connection in Neuroblox.
This is essentially the page,
exactly like the notebook.
And the notebook name is the
blox connections are here.
So yeah, please
open the notebook.
And if you have any
questions about the talk,
feel free to ask now.
Otherwise, you can start
with the exercises.
And yeah, ask us anytime.